Guide to the Northern Virginia Civil War images collection, 1853-1914
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Northern Virginia Civil War images collection
1853-1914
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
C0150
3 linear feet
The collection contains images and maps depicting Northern Virginia. A majority of the images are contemporary illustrations of the Civil War in Virginia. Formats include wood engravings, steel engravings, lithographs, chromolithographs, and a manuscript.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased by Special Collections and Archives in 1997-2005 from Prints Old and Rare.
Historical Information
The Illustrated London News was one of the first newspapers to employ wood engravings on a wide scale. One of its artists was Frank Vizetelly (1830-1883); he covered the Civil War for British readers. Early on, he illustrated the war from the Union side but was later allowed to draw from the Confederate side. Artists like Vizetelly sometimes did more than draw, though. He acted as a messenger for Confederate General James Longstreet at the battle of Chickamauga. Vizetelly was also a staff aide for the Confederates at the battle of Fredericksburg and was present at Charleston, South Carolina, when it was besieged. Because of such personal involvement by artists, many engravings were not made by detached observers, but by active participants in history unfolding.
Frank Leslie (1821-1880) was another artist who began his career as an engraver in 1842 and eventually published his own newspaper, which he titled, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper. The newspaper also covered the Civil War. Leslie used a large number of illustrations in his newspaper to increase circulation. Images from Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper are well represented in Northern Virginia Images Collection, including several images from the German language edition of the newspaper.
Another popular periodical of the time was Harper's Weekly. It first appeared in 1857 and became one of the most important and influential periodicals in nineteenth century America, notably during the Civil War. Two prominent artists for Harper's Weekly during this period were Alfred Waud (1828-1891) and Thomas Nast (1840-1902). Engravings by both are included in Northern Virginia Images Collection. Waud was primarily assigned to the eastern front and covered the war from the Battle of First Manassas to the Confederacy's surrender at Appomattox Court House. Thomas Nast (who later became famous for creating the roly- poly figure in red we now know as Santa Claus) worked largely in New York for most of the war. One of the major exceptions to this was when he spent time in the Union camp during the Battle of Gettysburg. Nast's sympathies were for the Union side, which, naturally, bothered Southerners, who often sent threatening letters to Nast at the Harper's Weekly office. By and large, The Illustrated London News, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, and Harper's Weekly illustrated the Civil War from the Northern point-of-view.
Many of today's Northern Virginia residents only know the area as a population outgrowth of Washington, D.C. Despite this cosmopolitan reputation, it was largely farm country at the time of the Civil War through World War II. Few realize that the area was the frequent battleground for large contending forces. Yet, many of the areas that are depicted in the images still exist today but under much different circumstances. Some of the areas included in these images have undergone radical cultural changes as well. An Islamic Mosque now occupies Munson Hill, which Confederate forces occupied under General J.E.B. Stuart during early days of the war.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of nearly 200 images on various historical subjects in a variety of formats, including wood engravings, steel engravings, lithographs, chromolithographs, maps, and manuscripts. Most of the images depict battles and maps of the Civil War. The maps include the cities of Arlington and Alexandria and the counties of Fairfax, Loudoun and Prince William. Columbia Pike, Chain Bridge, Long Bridge, the Little River Turnpike, Centreville and Manassas all existed at the time of the Civil War and all of them are represented or referenced in these images.
Most of the Civil War images are from three periodicals: The Illustrated London News, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, and Harper's Weekly. They are primarily wood engravings, several of which are hand colored. Though wood engraving was invented as an illustrative technique in the 1790s, it was the later appearance of the mass illustrated newspaper that took advantage of the technique to appeal to a wide readership.
Although pictorial images comprise the majority of images in the collection, there are also numerous maps, most of which were produced by lithography. A number were produced for military purposes and employed by both the North and South alike. Maps made during the Civil War were often exceedingly accurate; their usefulness carried on into the twentieth century.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by locality of primary image.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the, the, and the the WRLC digital collection. The is available for GMU affiliated researchers.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
Virginia, Northern--Maps.; Virginia, Northern--Pictorial works.
Subjects:
Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Maps.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Pictorial works.
Document Types:
Chromolithographs.; Lithographs.; Maps.; Steel engravings.; Wood engravings.
Contents List
- Northern Virginia Civil War images collection
  - [Acquia] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 1)
    - A. Road From Alexandria to Washington; B. Attack on Acquia Creek Battery by United States Steamers "Pawnee", "Anacostia", and "Freeborn"; C. Arlington House, The Home of General Robert E. Lee, Commander of the Confederate Army, June 1861; unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
      The Pictorial Battles of the Civil War
    - Action at Acquia Creek Between United States Vessels and Rebel Batteries, June 22, 1861; unnumbered; Wood Engraving
      Harper's Weekly
    - The Attack upon the Confederate Batteries at the Entrance of Aquia Creek, Potomac River, by the United States Vessels "Pawnee," "Yankee," "Thomas Freeborn," "Anacosta" and "Resolute, June 1st, 1861; unnumbered; Wood Engraving; 8 3/4" x 14"
      The Soldier in Our Civil War
    - The Attack upon the Batteries at the Entrance of Aquia Creek, Potomac River, by the United States Vessels "Pawnee," "Yankee," "Thomas Freeborn," "Anacosta" and "Resolute, June 1, 1861; 1.7; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 8 3/4" x 14"
    - Bombardment der von den Sezessionisten an der Mundung des Aquia Creek in den Potomac aufgewarfenen Batterien durch Ver. Staaten Kriegsschiffe, am 1. June 1861, June 1, 1861; 1.8; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14 1/4"
      Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper [German Language Edition]
    - The Attack on the Secession Batteries at Aquia Creek, Potomac River, by the U. S. Vessels Pawnee, Live Yankee,Freeborn, Anacosta and Lioness, June 1st, 1861, June 15, 1861; 1.25; Wood Engraving; 8 3/4" x 14"
      Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
  - [Alexandria] (Folder 2)
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 1.A, 4.1; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
      by Charles Magnus
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 1.A, 4.2; Hand Colored Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 2.C, 4.3; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 5.A, 4.4; Lithograph; 3" x 3 1/4"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 2.B, 4.5; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 3.B, 4.6; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 4.B, 4.7; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 1.C, 4.8; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 3.A, 4.9; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 3.C, 4.10; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 4.C, 4.11; Lithograph; 3" x 5"
    - Bird's Eye View of Alexandria, VA. No. 5.C, 4.12; Lithograph; 3" x 3 1/4"
    - The Civil War in America: Unionist Scouting Party in the Virginian Woods in the Neighborhood of Alexandria, July 13, 1861, 4.14; Wood Engraving; 6 1/2" x 9 1/4"
      The Illustrated London News
    - The Michigan Regiment and the Ellsworth Zouaves Working at the Breastworks in the Outskirts of Alexandria, Fairfax, VA, June 15, 1861; 4.15; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 8" x 9 1/4"
    - The Naval Brigade, Lieutenant Perkins Commanding, Constructing the Main Battery on Shutter's Hill to Guard Alexandria, VA., and Command the Fairfax Road, 4.16; Wood Engraving; 9" x 14 1/2"
    - The First Michigan Regiment and the Ellsworth Zouaves in the Entrenchments at Alexandria, VA., 4.16; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 8" x 9 1/4"
      The Civil War in the United States
    - The Naval Brigade Constructing the Marine Battery on Shutter's Hill, to Guard Alexandria, VA., and Command the Fairfax Road, Lieutenant Perkins Commanding, August 10, 1861, 4.17; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14 1/4"
    - Interior of Fort Runyon, near Alexandria, Virginia, 4.17A; Wood Engraving; 3 1/2" x 8 3/4"
    - Fort Albany, Near Alexandria, Virginia, 4.17B; Wood Engraving; 3 1/2" x 8 3/4"
    - The Civil War in America: Embarkation of a Portion of the Army of the Potomac at Alexandria, near Washington, May 3, 1862, 4.18; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 4 3/4" x 13 1/2"
    - Company of Secession Cavalry Surrendering to Colonel Wilcox, of the First Michigan Regiment, in front of the Slave-Pen at Alexandria, June 15, 1861, 4.19; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 7" x 13 3/4"
    - The Fairfaxes of Virginia, 4.20
      Journal Article with Print Reproductions
    - Army of General Banks on the March to Alexandria, June 13, 1863, 4.21; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 7" x 9 1/4"
    - Zouaves Building Entrenchments at Shuter's Hill, near Alexandria, 4.22A; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 14"
      by A. Waud; Pictorial Battles of the Civil War
    - Commencement of the Action at Bull Run - Sherman's Battery Engaging the Enemy's Masked Battery, 4.22B; Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 14"
    - Erschiekung des Ubersten E. E. Ellsworth durch James W. Jackson in dem "Marshall House" zu Alexandria, Virginien, am 24. Mai 1861, 4.23; Wood Engraving; 14 1/2" x 20"
    - The Civil War in America: Unionist Scouting Party in the Virginian Woods in the Neighborhood of Alexandria, July 13, 1861, 4.24; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 6 1/2" x 9 1/4"
    - Historic Alexandria Virginia the Home Town of George Washington, 4.25
      by the Alexandria Chamber of Commerce; City Brochure with Photographs and Map
    - The Naval Brigade, Lieutenant Perkins Commanding, Constructing the Main Battery on Shutter's Hill to Guard Alexandria, VA., and Command the Fairfax Road, 4.27; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9" x 14 1/2"
      The Soldier in our Civil War
  - [Annandale] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 3)
    - The Civil War in America: Advanced Post of General Blenker's Division Surprised at Anandale, Virginia, by Confederate Cavalry, Janurary 18, 1862; 17.1; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 13 1/2"
  - [Arlington] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 4)
    - Arlington Cemetery, Arlington, Virginia, Monument to Unknown Union Soldiers, Undated, unnumbered
    - Arlington House, the Seat of G. W. P. Custis, Esq., September, 1853, 6.1; Wood Engraving; 6" x 4 1/4"
      Harper's New Monthly Magazine, No. XL - Vol. VII
    - At Arlington, VA., The Headquarters of General Runyon's New Jersey Brigade, 6.3; Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
    - Arlington, May 29, 1886, 6.4; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 13 3/4" x 9"
      by Charles Graham; Harper's Weekly
    - Tomb of 2111 Unknown Soldiers, Arlington Cemetery, 6.5A; Reproduced Photograph; 5" x 3 3/4"
      by Bell; Harper's Weekly
    - The Old Lee Mansion in the Arlington Cemetery, Virginia, 6.5B; Reproduced Photograph; 2 3/4" x 5"
    - Admiral Porter's Grave, Arlington Cemetary, 6.5C; Reproduced Photograph; 2 3/4" x 3"
    - General Sheridan's Grave, Arlington Cemetery, 6.5D; Reproduced Photograph; 4 1/2" x 3 1/4"
    - Amphitheatre, Arlington, from which Addresses Are Delivered on Decoration Days, 6.5E; Reproduced Photograph; 3" x 4"
    - Smoke Rising from the Firing of national Salute of Twenty-One Guns at Conclusion of the Ceremonies, 6.7; Reproduced Photograph; 9 1/4" x 14 1/4"
      by National Photo Co.
    - Camp Corcoran, on Arlington Heights, VA., near Washington - The Sixty-Ninth Regiment, N. Y. S. M., Digging Trenches and Erecting Breastworks, 6.8; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
    - Arlington House (Formerly Residence of Gen. Robert E. Lee), 6.10; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 5" x 4 1/2"
      Picturesque Washington
    - Burial of the Late Admiral David D. Porter, at Arlington, VA. - Performing the Last Rites, March 7, 1891, 6.11; Reproduced Photograph; 6" x 8 3/4"
      by Bell; Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
    - Views of beautiful Arlington, VA.: Ft. Myer Gate; Rough Riders Monument; Spanish War Nurses Monument; Officers' Section; Wireless Towers at Radio Station; Field of the Dead; Confederate Memorial; The "Maine" Anchor; Soldiers' and Sailors' Monument; Custis-Lee Mansion; The Temple of Fame; Tomb of the Unknown Dead; Memorial Amphitheater; Statue of Gen. Phil. Kearny; Graves of George Washington Parke Custer and Wife; Mast of Maine; Sheridan Monument, 6.12; Reproduced Photographs; 3' 2" x 5 3/4"
      Published by The Gray Line Sight Seeing Tours
    - Arlington, VA.: Fort Myer Gate; Custis Lee mansion; Temple of Fame; Washington from Arlington; Tomb of Unknown Dead; Officer's Section; Sheridan monument; Memorial Amphitheater; Tomb of Unknown Soldier; Mast of the Maine; Tomb of General Nelson A. Miles; Rough Riders' Monument; Robert E. Peary Memorial, Discoverer of the North Pole; Kearny Statue; Soldiers' and Sailors' Monument of the Spanish War; Confederate Memorial; General Crook Monument, 6.13; Reproduced Photographs; 3" x 3' 4 1/4"
      Published by B. S. Reynolds Co.
    - Beautiful Arlington, VA.: Memorial Amphitheater; Custis Lee Mansion; Tomb of the Unknown Soldier of the World War; World War Section and Arlington Wireless Towers; Field of the Dead; Tomb of the unknown Dead; The Temple of Fame; General Wheeler and Officers; View of Washington from Arlington, VA.; The General Wheeler Monument; Gen. Sheridan's Grave; Soldiers' and Sailors' Monument; McClellan Gate; Custis Family Lot; Mast of the Maine and Graves of Her Dead; Kearny Statue; Admiral Dewey's Tomb; General Crook Monument; Sheridan Gate; Grave of Robert E. Peary; Confederate memorial; Old Amphitheater; Interior of Memorial Amphitheater; Rough Riders' Monument; Main Entrance, Arlington national Cemetery; Ord and Weitzel Gate, 6.14; Reproduced Photographs; 3' 3" x 5 3/4"
      Published by the Post Exchange, Fort Myer, VA.
    - Camp Corcoran, on Arlington Heights -- the Sixty-Ninth, N.Y.S.M., Digging Trenches and Erecting Breastworks -- Company inspection by Superior Officers -- Georgetown in the Distance, 6.15A; Hand colored wood engraving; 9 1/4" x 13 1/4"
      Pictorial History of the War of 1861
    - The Marshall House, Corner of Pitt and King Streets, Alexandria, VA., Where Colonel Ellsworth was Assassinated, 6.15B; Wood engraving; 6 1/4" x 6"
    - At Arlington, VA., The Headquarters of General Runyon's New Jersey Brigade, 6.16; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
    - Freedman's Village, Arlington, Virginia, May 7, 1864, 6.17; Wood Engraving
  - [Bailey's Cross Road] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 5)
    - Sutler's Cart at Bailey's Cross Road, December 2, 1861, 12.1; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 13 3/4"
      by A. Waud; The New-York Illustrated News
    - The Great Review at Bailey's Cross Roads, Virginia, on November 20, 1861, December 7, 1861, 12.2; Wood Engraving; 9" x 19 3/4"
  - [Budd's Ferry] [This folder contains two prints of each image.] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 6)
    - The Civil War in America: The Confederate Batteries on the Lower Potomac, Virginia Shore, Opposite Budd's Ferry - Government Store-Schooners Running the Blockade, December 7, 1861, 16.A; Wood Engraving; 4 1/4" x 13 3/4"
    - The Civil War in America: The Ten-Pounder Gun Battery (Federalist) at Budd's Ferry, Lower Potomac, Opposite the Confederate Batteries on the Virginia Shore, December 7, 1861, 16.B; Wood Engraving; 5" x 13 3/4"
  - [Burkesville Station] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 7)
    - Surrender of Lee's Army - Collecting the Captured Rebel Muskets at Burkesville Station, Virginia, Previous to Sending Them North, May 27, 1865, 1.A; Wood Engraving
      By J. Becker; Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
  - [Catlett] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 8)
    - Catlett's Station on the Orange and Alexandria Railroad, Virginia, Now Held by the Excelsior Brigade, 13.A; Wood Engraving; 4" x 9"
  - [Centreville] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 9)
    - Confederate Position Near Centreville VA, at the Crossing of the Orange and Alexandria Railway over Bull Run, Showing Confederate Encampment Fortifications, unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - Centreville, Virginia, to Which General Pope Withdrew his Army on August 30 September 13, 1862, 7.2A; Wood Engraving; 4 3/4" x 13 3/4"
      by Mr. A. R. Waud; Harper's Weekly
    - Manassas Junction, Intersection of the Manassas Gap and Orange and Alexandria Railroads - Scene of Several Recent Fights September 13, 1862, 7.2B; Wood Engraving; 4 3/4" x 13 3/4"
    - Blenker's Brigade Covering the Retreat near Centreville, July, 1861, 7.3; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
      Harper's Pictorial History of the Civil War
    - The Civil War in America: Federals Advancing on the Abandoned Confederate Positions at Centreville, April 12, 1862, 7.4; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 13 1/2"
    - The Civil War in America: A Portion of the Abandoned Confederate Works and Camp at Centreville, April 26, 1862, 7.5; Wood Engraving; 6 3/4" x 9 1/4"
    - The Evacuated Rebel Positions near Centreville, VA., at the Crossing of the Orange and Alexandria Railway over Bull Run, Showing Abandoned Rebel Encampment, Fortifications, Etc., 7.6; Wood Engraving; 5 1/4" x 14"
    - Principal Rebel Defences at Centreville, Showing the Forts, Breastworks, Log Barracks, Etc., With the Quaker or Wooden Guns in the Embrasures, April 12, 1862, 7.7; Wood Engraving; 6 1/4" x 14"
      by Mr. Forbes; Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper [same image as 7.8 in folder 9]
    - Principal Rebel Defences at Centreville, Showing the Forts, Breastworks, Log Barracks, Etc., With the Quaker or Wooden Guns in the Embrasures, April 12, 1862, 7.8; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 6 1/4" x 14"
      Pictorial History of the War of 1861 [same image as 7.7 in folder 9]
    - The War in Virginia - View of the Town of Centreville, VA., With the Battlefield of Bull Run, Bull Run Mountains, Thoroughfare Gap, and the Blue Ridge in the Distance, November 28, 1863, 7.9; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
      by Edwin Forbes; Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
    - Blenker's Brigade Covering the Retreat near Centreville, July, 1861, 7.10A; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
    - The Battle-Field of Bull Run July, 1861, 7.10B; Wood Engraving; 9 3/4" x 9"
    - Confederate Huts at Centreville, March 1862; 7.11A; Wood Engraving
  - [Chancellorsville] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 10)
    - Hooker in Command - Chancellorsville; Head-Quarters at the Army of the Potomac, January-April 1863, unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 14" x 9 1/4"
      Same image as 20.9 in folder 10
    - Attack on General Sedgwick's Corps, on Monday, May 4th, 1863, as Seen from Falmouth Heights, 3.4; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 14"
      by Edwin Forbes; The Soldier in Our Civil War
    - Battle of Chancellorsville, VA - Attack on General Sedgwick's Corps on Monday, May 4th, 1863 at 5 P.M. as Seen from Falmouth Heights, 3.11; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 14"
      Same image as 3.4 in folder 10
    - Head-Quarters at the Army of the Potomac, April 18, 1863, 20.9; Wood Engraving; 14" x 9 1/4"
  - [Culpeper] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 11)
    - The War in Virginia - Culpeper Court House, October 17, 1863, unnumbered; Wood Engraving
    - The Army of the Potomac: A. General Custer Charging up the Hill upon the Enemy's Guns; B. General Gregg's Troops Going into Action; C. Signal Station on Pony Mountain; D. Culpepper from the Northwest; E. Butler's Battery Going into Position; F. The Army of the Potomac - General Buford Attacking the Enemy at Raccoon Ford, September 14, 1863, unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
      By A. R. Waud; Harper's Weekly
    - Capture of Stuart's Confederate Guns, near Culpepper, by General Custer's Cavalry Brigade, September 14, 1863, 15.4; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
  - [Dumfries] [This folder contains two prints of each image.] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 12)
    - General Haupt's Bridge over Potomac Creek, Virginia, Destroyed by the Rebels, August 29, 1863, 11.A; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 3 3/4" x 13 3/4"
    - Dumfries, Virginia, August 29, 1863, 11.B; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 5 1/2" x 13 3/4"
  - [Edward's Ferry, Harper's Ferry, Camp Princeton] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 13)
    - Camp Princeton, Virginia, the Headquarters of Gen. Runyon's New Jersey Brigade, July 13, 1861, 6.2; Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
    - View from Loudoun Heights, VA., Showing Harper's Ferry, Maryland Heights, Bolivar, Etc., 18.1; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
    - Engagement between the National Troops and the Rebels, on the Virginia Side of the Potomac, opposite Edwards' Ferry, on 22nd October -- Battery of Parrot Guns on Maryland Shore, November 16, 1861, 20.32A; Hand colored wood engraving; 6" x 20"
    - Successful Retreat of the National Troops from the Virginian Shore across a Canal Boat Bridge at Edwards' Ferry, on the Night of 23rd October, November 16, 1861, 20.32B; Hand colored Wood engraving; 8" x 20"
  - [Fair Oaks] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 14)
    - Ausgraben gefallener Unionsoldaten von Fair Oaks und Seven Pines, unnumbered; Wood Engraving
    - Bayonet Charge of the Second Excelsior Regiment, Colonel Hall, at the Battle of Fairoaks, June, 1862, August 16, 1862, 20.10; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 13 3/4"
    - The Army of the Potomac - Furious Attack of the Rebels on Kirby's Battery at the battle of Fairoaks, July 5, 1862, 20.11A; Wood Engraving; 4 1/2" x 13 3/4"
      by Mr. Mead; Harper's Weekly
    - The Army of the Potomac - Captain Wheeler's Battery Struck by Lightning, July 5, 1862, 20.11B; Wood Engraving; 4 3/4" x 13 3/4"
    - Fair Oaks Farm - Burying the Dead and Burning the Horses, June 1862; 20.34; Wood Engraving
      On the Shenandoah and the Chickahominy
  - [Fairfax] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 15)
    - The War in America: Texan Rangers (Federalists) Reconnoitring between Alexandria and Fairfax, Virginia, unnumbered; Wood Engraving
    - The Civil War in America: Carolonian Pickets Flying before the Advance of the Federal Troops on Fairfax, August 17, 1861, unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 6 1/2" x 9 1/4"
    - The Civil War in America: Carolonian Pickets Flying before the Advance of the Federal Troops on Fairfax, August 17, 1861, unnumbered; Wood Engraving; 6 1/2" x 9 1/4"
    - The Civil War in America: Confederate Prisoners Captured by United States' Pickets between Fairfax and Manassas Junction, Virginia, August 17, 1861, 8.1; Wood Engraving; 8" x 9 1/4"
      The Illustrated London News, 2 prints
    - Gallant Charge of Federal Cavalry Into Fairfax Courthouse, Virginia, June 22, 1861; 8.1A; Hand Colored Wood Engraving